A Guide to the Historic Neighborhood and Building Reports, 1978-2008
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Historic Neighborhood and Building Reports, 1978-2008
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 30
2 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
These reports are donated to the library by the various authors.
Scope and Content
Record Group 30 houses miscellaneous reports written about Arlington County neighborhoods and specific buildings that are historical in nature. These reports are, for the most part, unpublished works done by students of Historic Preservation from local colleges and universities, county generated studies, or Historic American Buildings Surveys (HABS). This active collection currently is 2.5 linear feet.
The subjects covered include neighborhoods, communities and buildings in Arlington. Most are well documented, and were written from the 1980s to the present. These reports contain histories of the neighborhood or property and analysis of its architectural importance. Many of these reports also contain photographs; there are 71 total images in the collection. Files with an asterisk contain photographs.
Arrangement
Subgroup 1 contains reports on neighborhoods, with every neighborhood given its own series. Subgroup 2 contains reports on historic buildings and other properties. Each property has its own series. All folder titles in quotes are the actual titles of the reports. This arrangement was created by the archivist.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Neighborhoods.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Historic Neighborhood Reports
  - Addison Heights
    - "Real Property Valuation of 1915 and 1919 S. Arlington Ridge Road," 1989 * (Box 1)
  - Arlington View
    - "Arlington View," 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ashton Heights
    - "Neighborhood History Preservation Study for the Ashton Heights Area of Arlington County, VA," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Barcroft
    - "Barcroft," 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Churches of the Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
    - "Commercial Area of Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
    - "Demographic Data of Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
    - "History of Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
    - "Residential Area of Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
    - "Schools of Barcroft Community," n.d. (Box 1)
  - Cherrydale
    - "Cherrydale: An Example of 20th Century Suburban American Development in Arlington County, Virginia," 1987 * (Box 1)
    - "Historic Preservation Survey of the Cherrydale Hardware Store/Cherrydale Masonic Lodge Building, 3805 Lee Highway, Arlington, Virginia," 1988 (Box 1)
  - Clarendon
    - "Clarendon Task Force on Open Space and Historical Designation Final Report," 1988 (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village
    - "Colonial Village: The Cultural and Architectural Heritage," 1978 (Box 1)
  - Columbia Pike
    - "Two Hundred Years of Transportation: Historic Columbia Pike in 2008, A Preservation Plan," 2008 (Box 1)
  - Dawson Terrace
    - "Dawson Terrace," 1988 (Box 1)
  - East Falls Church
    - "Historic Preservation Survey of the East Falls Church Neighborhood of Arlington County," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Fairlington/Shirlington
    - "Fairlington/Shirlington: A Preservation Survey," n.d. (Box 1)
  - Fostoria
    - "Fostoria: A Community Where Arlington's Past is Present," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Glencarlyn
    - "Historic Neighborhood Designation: Glencarlyn," 1987 (Box 1)
  - Hall's Hill/High View Park
    - "Neighborhood History Preservation Study: Hall's Hill/High View Park, Arlington, Virginia," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Lyon Park
    - "Historical Analysis of Lyon Park," 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Neighborhood History Preservation Study: Lyon Park Neighborhood," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Lyon Village
    - "Lyon Village," 1987 * (Box 1)
  - Rock Spring
    - "The Story of Rock Spring Road," 1989 (Box 2)
- Historic Buidling Reports
  - Abingdon
    - "Historic Preservation vs. National Airport," n.d. [1] (Box 2)
    - "Historic Preservation vs. National Airport," n.d. [2] (Box 2)
    - "Historic Preservation vs. National Airport," n.d. [3] (Box 2)
  - Buckingham
    - Historic American Buildings Survey Documentation, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Historic American Buildings Survey Photograph Index and Key, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Historic American Buildings Survey Photographs, 1994 [1]* (Box 2)
    - Historic American Buildings Survey Photographs, 1994 [2]* (Box 2)
    - Historic American Buildings Survey Photographs, 1994 [3]* (Box 2)
  - Lawyer's Row
    - Transmittal Letter, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Lawyer's Row Block Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - General Views, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - "Ball Building Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Ball Building Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Jesse Building Survey Report, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Jesse Building Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Jesse-Hosmer Building Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Jesse-Hosmer Buidling Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Moncure Building Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Moncure Building Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Rucker Building Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Rucker Buidling Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
    - Simmonds Building Survey Report, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Simmonds Building Survey Photographs, 1990 * (Box 2)
  - Glebe House
    - Glebe House, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Glenmore
    - Glenmore/Glass House History, 1983, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Harry Gray Homestead
    - "The History, Heritage, Legacy of the Harry W. Gray Homestead" (Box 2)